THE COUNSELOR

Dan Simmons

Introduction

(from Obsessions)

Dan Simmons writes really huge mutli-layered books. He is the author of Song of Kali, Carrion Comfort, Hyperion, The Fall of Hyperion, among others.

Dan was supposed to write something short for us, but he said he didn’t have time so he wrote something long. We’re glad hid did. This novella is filled with suspense, dark humor, violence, and yet, its humanity will touch you.

You’ll never forget “The Counselor”.

—Gary Raisor

He was a quiet man of moderate height who wore glasses that gave him a slightly owlish look. The district assigned him to three schools: Loma Linda Elementary, Myers Middle School, and RFK High. Only in the high school did they have an office for him; in the other two he made do in converted storage rooms off the cafeterias. The plaque he set out did not carry his name and had only the single word: COUNSELOR.

As was the case with most school counselors, the administration tended to forget him, teachers tended to mistrust him, and the students were embarrassed to come to him. Despite the lack of welcome or cooperation, he made it his business to visit every classroom and to introduce himself. Then he went to his tiny office to wait.

For weeks he sat alone much of the day, confirming the prejudices of most of the teachers: school counselors were little more than loafers, misguided do-gooders too lazy or too timid to teach. But then, slowly, most informally, the children began to drop by. Some would look in out of curiosity. Some would come drawn by the magic word “Counselor,” sensing that here was someone who—if not necessarily on their side—might be neutral in an environment where grownups seemed a monolithic mass of rule-makers and punishment-givers. Others, especially the trouble-makers and near-drop-outs who roamed the halls most freely and frequently, began to drop by on their way to the office or detention hall, sometimes coming in to put their sneakers up on the Counselor’s desk and talk while waiting for the machinery of discipline to begin grinding its gears.

They all found the same thing: the Counselor listened. Sometimes he asked questions in that soft voice of his, occasionally he would offer them a mint from the bowl on his desk, but always he listened. He did not advise. He did not refer. He did not pass judgment on what the students told him, no matter how petty or outrageous. In an environment where the adults spoke almost incessantly, usually pausing only to demand answers to their questions, the students soon realized that the Counselor spoke almost not at all. He listened, nodded, clarified, chatted, and invariably rose to shake the student’s hand when he or she left. He shook hands with hulking, six-foot-three high school seniors who came to discuss their drug problems; he shook hands with tense and pimply fourteen-year-old girls who came to discuss their insecurity and lack of friends; he shook hands with seven-year-old second graders who dropped by to show him their teddy bears.

Kids soon learned that the Counselor could quickly tell bullshit from the truth. The bullshitters soon quit coming, for although the Counselor rarely challenged them, his small smile told them that he knew they were not telling the truth. The others came more often because of that. He listened to them.

It seemed he did nothing else. Occasionally the Counselor would be called to a staffing—one of those formal meetings where administrators, teachers, specialists, and cowed parents meet before or after school to decide special placement or procedures for a student—but he had little or nothing to say at these meetings and was invited more rarely as the school year progressed.

The Counselor listened. After a year, a significant portion of the population at each school had visited him. After two years, everyone knew him. The teachers held him in universal contempt, their suspicions confirmed that a counselor did nothing but sit in his office and drink coffee most of the day. Many teachers were irritated by him, for although he never took sides in disputes with their students—indeed, never discussed what the children had said during their visits, not even to correct a problem or “personality conflict” in the classroom—the teachers suspected that he was on the kids’ sides more than theirs. The principal at each school tolerated the Counselor, accepting him as someone forced on them by the Central Administration. The principals knew that the School Board thought it looked good to have “a school counselor in each building,” despite the fact that he was only in the building one and a half days a week and appeared to do nothing. The principals felt sure that as soon as the next budget crunch came along, the Counselor would be the first to go. They always were. In the meantime, this counselor did not get in the way much and used almost no supplies.

Each day the Counselor sat in his room, the door slightly open, Bach playing softly from the small tape player on his desk, and waited. A few students had appointments, but most simply dropped in. They knew where to find him.

And when they did, he listened.

“At first he didn’t used to hit me much, but these days, he hits me a lot of the time.”

“With his hands?”

“Yeah.”

“Like a slap? Or with his fist?”

“Both. When he’s real drunk, he uses his fist. He . . . you know . . . he hits me high on the arm, or in the stomach, or on the legs. Places where the bruises won’t show when I go to school.”

“Does he ever use anything else to hit you with?”

“His belt sometimes. Once he used a whatchamacallit, you know, a curtain rod. He pulled it off my window and hit me in the back of the legs with it.”

“And you say it’s gotten worse since he was laid off?”

“Yeah.”

There was a long moment of silence. The Counselor pushed the bowl of mints closer to the girl. She took one, unwrapped it, took a minute to chew it. She was nine years old and her name was Maria Consuela Vigil. She pronounced it Vee-hill. The man they were talking about was her stepfather. She had never mentioned his name but the Counselor had checked the school records and knew that it was Tomas Calderon, thirty-nine. He had been laid off from the tire factory for nine months now.

“It used to be,” said Maria, shifting the mint to her cheek so that she could speak again, “that he used to hit me when I did something wrong . . . like not have dinner ready on time or forget to go get his beer. But now he just does it when he gets home even if I haven’t done anything.”

The Counselor nodded slightly. “Did you ask your mother to help in getting him to stop?”

Maria began to chew at a finger, saw the reddened, close-bitten nail there, and set her hands on her lap and folded them shut. “Yes. But Momma gets awful headaches. She says he’s the man of the house and we all have to do a better job to make him happy.”

“Have you told anyone else?”

“Uh-uh. I tried to tell Mrs. Hopper once, but she said she had her own problems.”

The Counselor took a mint and nodded again. Mrs. Hopper was Maria’s fourth-grade teacher. The woman had been at Loma Linda for eighteen years and had never reported a possible case of child abuse or referred a child to a counselor or school psychologist. The Counselor had checked the records.

“OK,” he said, “it must be about time for recess to be over. You want to line up with your class outside?”

“Yeah,” said Maria and stood a moment by the door. “You’re not going to tell anybody, are you?”

The Counselor shot the mint wrapping at the wastebasket in the corner. It fell short. He stooped to pick it up, rose, shook hands with Maria at the door, and said softly, “No, I won’t tell anyone.”

The talk in the Loma Linda teacher’s lounge was usually about how tired everyone was, how stupid the kids were, and how useless the new Administration-mandated math curriculum was. Occasionally the only male teacher on the staff tried to start a sports conversation with the Counselor, but gave up when he realized that the Counselor really didn’t care about sports.

The Counselor was rarely included in the conversation, but he ate lunch there every day anyway.

Occasionally Mrs. Hopper or one of the other teachers would engage him in conversation that seemed like friendly banter but was really an attack on his job.

“Admit it,” she said on the Wednesday that Maria had visited him, “aren’t the figures for the so-called child abuse absurdly overblown?”

The Counselor adjusted his glasses, sipped milk from the small carton through a straw, and seemed to consider the comment for some time. “No,” he said at last in that maddeningly soft voice of his, “if anything, the figures are absurdly underestimated. Last year there were almost two point three million cases of child abuse reported to various social services. That included more than a hundred and forty-two thousand cases of sexual molestation of minors—usually by members of the immediate family. If you accept the figure that only fifteen to twenty percent of the actual cases are reported, then there may be fifteen million children being abused annually.”

Mrs. Hopper laughed. “That’s just what I mean. It’s absurd. There’s no possibility that that many parents are truly hurting their kids. Not that a few of these children couldn’t use a little corporal punishment. God knows the schools used to be a lot quieter and the kids more well-behaved when we were allowed to really discipline them.”

The Counselor smiled slightly and finished his milk with a slurp. Mrs. Hopper and Mrs. Burdett went out whispering. The Counselor stayed there alone to finish his carrot cake. He was the only one who did not have to rush to pick up a class from lunch recess. The teachers knew that and added it as another mark on their resentment list.

Tomas Calderon came out of the Red Door Tavern a little after two a.m. and began walking up the alley toward Third Street and home. It had been a shitty night. He’d spent most of his wife’s check on drinks and lost the rest in a pool game with Ernie and the boys. When he got home, he thought he’d check to see if his dinner was hot. If it wasn’t he’d wake up Donna or that goddamn brat of hers, Maria Consuela. It was really Maria’s job to keep his dinner warm.

It had goddamn better be hot.

He turned the corner in the alley and stopped. Between him and the opening onto Third Street, some guy dressed all in black was standing there. Tomas’s first response was to be startled—the guy seemed to be all black, black turtleneck sweater, black pants, black combat boots, even a black ski mask—but then Tomas saw he was just a little punk and his gloved hands were empty. Tomas carried the five-inch French switchblade his cousin Ernesto had given him years ago.

“What the fuck you want?” Tomas realized that his voice was a little slurred but that he was sobering up quickly. He took two steps toward the guy, reached into his jacket pocket, and brought the knife out, blade opening with a soft click. He set his thumb on the top of the blade, lowered it to belly height, and began moving it back and forth the way he remembered from his gang days in the barrio. The fucker by the opening to the alley didn’t move. If it weren’t for the eyes in the mask openings catching what little light seeped in here from the streetlight, Tomas would have thought the thing was one of those store dummies, all dressed in black and left out here in the alley.

“Out of my way, pendejo.” Tomas stepped closer.

The man in black moved then, shifting left to bar Tomas’s way. The man in black’s hands were still empty.

“OK,” said Tomas, shrugging and grinning. “Hey, man, you got as much right as me to be here, I guess. Que no? I’ll go the fucking long way home.” Tomas turned his back on the man and pretended to fold the knife away as he took a step back the way he had come.

The man did not move. Tomas turned quickly, leaped forward, crouched, and brought the knife out and in quickly. He remembered the feeling of a blade slamming into someone’s belly, remembered the feel through his knife hand and arm as the blade travelled upward, found the heart. This pendejo wouldn’t know what hit him.

The man in black arched his body sideways in a move as graceful as a toreador’s. Then he brought his left arm in to his body, letting Tomas’s knife hand pass through the gap but closing on his upper arm.

“Hey!” Tomas tried to pull away, but the man in black—little more than a shadow—brought his fist down once, twice. The knife fell onto the bricks of the alley and Tomas heard a loud snap as his femur broke.

He staggered back, arm hanging limply. “Hey, shit, man.” He raised his left fist.

The man in black stepped in close and went to work. Tomas had gone with Ernie to see professional boxing more than once; this guy had the speed of a welterweight and the punch of a middleweight. He worked professionally, moving Tomas back to the wall and getting in close, slamming blows to Tomas’s belly, moving back to jab at the face, sliding the occasional jab in between Tomas’s eyes. He broke a rib early on, then another one before Tomas began to slide down the wall.

He propped Tomas up and hit him with a left hook that took out three front teeth. He slapped Tomas fully awake and then broke his nose with a flat-handed slap of his thick glove. Then he went to work in earnest.

Before he began sliding down again, Tomas did not know if the man in black had merely battered his left eye shut or knocked it out of its socket. He could feel only blood and broken stumps where his teeth had been. It felt like one of the broken ribs had punctured a lung. The jagged end of the broken femur pressed under the skin of his right arm.

The man in black let him slide all the way to the alley pavement this time. He knelt on Tomas’s chest. “We’ll stop now,” the man whispered, his breath hot on Tomas’s face. “But I’ll be back soon. You can count on it. Three more visits at least.” He moved his knee, set his weight on Tomas’s shattered upper arm.

Tomas screamed. Blood and saliva spattered the man’s black ski mask.

“See what it’s like to live in fear, pendejo,” whispered the man in black.

Tomas lifted his head, trying to spit at the man’s face. The gloved fist came down quickly, right at his eyes, until it filled the world.

The principal of Myers Middle School—a sort of junior high which held grades six, seven, and eight—was named Bill Mastyk and he had the tradition of inviting each of his teachers out for a private drink and a talk during the year. Mastyk had been a principal for twenty-one years and had long since divided school administrators into two categories: the ulcer-ridden doomed ones and the laid-back survivors. Mastyk had joined the latter category many years before.

He went out with the Counselor in May of the man’s first year at Myers. They chatted about this and that; Mastyk quickly learned that the Counselor did not seem to enjoy talking about sports. Mostly it was the principal who did the talking, trying to feel the man out about the school, the faculty, and the kids. The Counselor listened.

“Hey,” Mastyk said at last, feeling his third gin and tonic beginning to work but not caring. The Counselor had been sipping beer. “Hey, I know you’re real serious about your job, but it isn’t a war, you know.”

The Counselor adjusted his round, horn-rimmed glasses. “It isn’t?” Mastyk smiled, although he wasn’t sure the other man was joking. “Well, is it? I mean, we’re just talking kids and families here, right?”

The Counselor sipped his beer. “There are more than twelve hundred confirmed deaths of children from abuse and family violence each year,” he said. “That’s the low-end figure. Most experts think the actual total is at least five thousand a year. If we take half that as a true figure, then in the ten years I’ve been a counselor, kids have suffered half as many deaths as the entire Vietnam War produced. Only this war doesn’t end.”

Bill Mastyk ordered another gin and tonic. There was silence until it arrived. He swirled the little plastic sword of a swizzle stick. “You were in the Marine Corps,” he said at last.

The Counselor blinked once but showed no other surprise at the comment. “That isn’t in my employment records.”

“Uh-uh,” said Mastyk, grinning again. “I called your previous districts. Talked to several of your old supervisors.”

“And?”

“And besides one of them knowing that you’d been a Marine in some sort of combined special unit during the Iran rescue thing . . . when was that, seventy-nine?”

“Nineteen eighty,” said the Counselor.

“Yeah, must’ve been right before you started teaching. Real fuck up, that hostage rescue Carter ordered, wasn’t it?”

“I wasn’t there,” said the Counselor. He glanced at his watch.

“Well, you’ve been a lot of places since,” said Mastyk. “Six school districts and fourteen schools in ten years. You like to move around, don’t you?”

The Counselor smiled. “Mr. Mastyk, did you find anything in your various phonecalls that suggested that my professional work was less than adequate?”

Mastyk frowned at his drink, frustrated at the way the conversation was going. Most of the teachers and staff loosened up after a couple of drinks, giving him a personal relationship that he could use later and usually some pivotal information besides. He realized that the Counselor had given him nothing. “No,” he said, thinking about how all the administrators he’d called had referred to the Counselor as “a loner” and “strange . . . keeps to himself.” But no one had said he was incompetent. “No, no problems. I was just curious.”

The Counselor stood. “I don’t blame you, Mr. Mastyk. I’d be curious about who was on my staff, too. You can’t be too careful about who comes in contact with children these days.” He offered his hand.

Confused, Mastyk shook it, feeling the strength there. Mastyk had been a fair to middling tavern arm wrestler in his youth in Iowa, and he knew handshakes, even one as deceptively soft as this one.

“Hey!” the principal called as the Counselor paused near the door. “If it’s a war, who’s winning?”

The Counselor smiled slightly, nodded, and was gone.

The boy was seven years old and he smelled. Children have almost no body odor, but this child’s clothing was rancid with dirt, sweat, and urine. His face had the sort of gray, indoors look that comes from grime and a poor diet. His hair looked as if it had been cut by a drunk wielding a pair of shears. Only the boy’s eyes were fully alive as he spoke.

“My mom . . . my real mom, not Aunt Stella? My mom isn’t home lots of times, you know? After my daddy left she went away with a guy named Earl, but I can’t go with them ’cause I’m too little, you know?

“Anyway, my sister Patricia, she’s eleven, she went with them, but something happened in Missouri or somewhere and Patricia got real sick. My mom says she may not come back, that people’re taking care of her there. Aunt Stella says that Mom and Earl can’t stay in one place too long, you know. He’s got something called a warrant out against him. That means that the cops don’t like him.

“I like Aunt Stella . . . she’s real old but real nice. I used to like it when Mom took me away, but I worry about it now. We stay in motels mostly. Earl doesn’t talk to me much. Mom drinks a lot, and when she does she gets sort of . . . well, cranky, I guess. When I wet my bed, I’ve got to clean it up and go to the Punishment Room for a while.”

The Counselor pushed the bowl of mints closer. “What’s the punishment room, Josh?” The seven-year-old’s name was Joshua Reynolds.

Josh took three mints and popped two into his mouth. When he spoke, it was around the candy. “Oh, it’s like a closet. I mean, it is a closet. It doesn’t have no lights or anything. No toilet either.”

“How long do you stay in the Punishment Room?”

Josh shrugged and unwrapped the third mint. “Once it was morning when Mom put me in it . . . I usually have my Accidents right before I wake up . . . and it was after dark, way after my bedtime, when Earl let me out.”

The Counselor nodded. He took no notes.

“Last night,” said Josh, barely understandable now with three mints in his cheek, “Mom made me go down in the basement of the motel where they got these washing machines where I clean the sheets and I was supposed to fold all the clothes, but I didn’t do a very good job. When I brought them up, she made me stand in the kitchen with my arms up like this.” He showed the Counselor by lifting his arms straight out, palms down.

“How long did you stand that way?”

Josh lowered his arms and concentrated. “Well, I could hear the football game Earl was watching in the other room. It was all of the second half, I guess. Maybe a little bit more.” Josh looked ashamed. “Mom said it woulda been shorter but I was a baby and cried.” He rubbed his upper arms. “They still sorta feel funny today, like they were asleep or something.”

The Counselor nodded, walked Josh back to his classroom, shook hands with him, went to the office, and brought the boy’s school records back to his office. “Aunt Stella” was actually Joshua’s mother’s first husband’s aunt, sixty-eight-years-old. She had taken care of Josh for nineteen months the first time Desiré Reynolds, his mother, had run off with Earl. A note on the bottom of Josh’s year-old first-grade enrollment card mentioned that the boy was to go home with no one except his “Aunt Stella,” that there was the potential for kidnapping by a mother wanted by the law for child abandonment and her boyfriend, a certain Earl Durner, wanted in three states for forgery, assault, and armed robbery.

A few questions to Josh’s current teacher, the principal, and office staff showed that no one had read or remembered the notation. According to the parent aide on playground duty after school, Josh was picked up occasionally by a couple in a blue van.

The Counselor put the files back without making a further notation.

Desiré Reynolds awoke with a terrible taste in her mouth and an even more terrible pain in her arms. She blinked, shook her head, and then screamed.

She was hanging by her arms in a dark place. For a second she was sure that she was still dreaming, or maybe tripping from the shit Earl had brought up from Tijuana last time, but the excruciating pain in her arms convinced her otherwise. This was real.

Desiré blinked in the darkness, realized that there was a little light coming from below her, for Chrissakes, and glanced down. She wished she hadn’t. She was hanging thirty or forty feet above a concrete floor where a naked trouble light illuminated some sort of shaft with rusting iron crossbraces and cobwebs. It was dark here near the top of the shaft, but she could see her feet silhouetted against that light. They were dangling in mid-air. She looked up. It was dark, there was some massive weight above her, but she could see and feel some sort of wide straps around her wrists. She seemed to be hanging from something—an unseen roof, a crossbar, something—hanging and dangling over thirty feet of air with a pain that felt like her arms were being pulled from their sockets.

Desiré screamed and kicked. Her body swung on the straps. She vomited, felt her head clear a bit, and screamed again. Then terror surged even higher as she realized that she might be pulling the straps loose. She held her breath and swung gently back and forth, her arms and wrists throbbing with pain.

What happened? She remembered coming back to the hotel after dropping the kid off at Stella’s. She remembered setting down the bag she’d brought from the liquor store, calling for Earl, going into the bedroom to find him sleeping on the floor . . . only not sleeping, there’d been blood on his mouth, his eyes were bruised shut . . . and then she had backed away, feeling the scream building up, but before she could scream the arms had come around her, the cloth had been pressed against her face . . .

Desiré retched again, identifying the taste of ether now. The leather straps creaked. She cried out again, more of a moan than a scream this time.

“It hurts like hell, doesn’t it?”

Desiré screamed and twisted, feeling the straps cut deeper into her wrists, seeing the single light three stories below strobing between her tennis shoes.

There was a man . . . a dark shape with eyes . . . crouched on some sort of ledge or niche four to six feet to her left. She could only see his eyes and a mass of black that might be his shoulders. “Help!” She had meant to shout but it came out a whisper. Desiré realized that she had wet her stretch pants.

“You may be wondering where you are,” said the black form. It was a man. His voice was insanely calm, almost conversational. “Well, it’s an old hotel that’s been abandoned for quite a few years. Oddly enough the elevator still works. The place has eight floors, but I thought it would be nice to stop here on the fourth.”

Desiré looked down. The concrete floor seemed miles below. The cords on her wrists seemed to be cutting to the bone. “What . . . why . . . I’ll pay you . . . don’t . . .”

“I have to be leaving now,” said the man. Desiré’s eyes had adjusted to the dim light well enough that she could see he was wearing some sort of hood or mask. Only his pale eyes and teeth reflected light.

He leaned forward with some sort of pole . . . light on steel . . . there was a blade on the end of the pole!

Desiré screamed and twisted. The complicated arrangement of thongs and straps above her right wrist severed.

This time her scream was so loud it echoed back up the elevator shaft. All one hundred eighty-three pounds of Desiré Reynolds twisted, swung, pivoted, and twirled as she now hung by one arm. Her legs pedaled air. Her feet seemed to have lead weights on them.

“You’d better grab the bar above you,” the man said softly.

Desiré grunted, looked up. Eight inches above her right hand, some sort of metal bar hung below what must be the elevator car. The bar only ran two-thirds the way across the base of the car and shaft, but it had at least eighteen inches clearance beneath the car’s floor. Desiré shook her head and hung limply, despite the pain in her right wrist.

The form shrugged. “I’m going to cut the second strap now.” The blade extended.

Desiré screamed, swung, tried to get her free left hand up there, failed, tried again, found steel under her fingers. The blade on the broomstick passed her wrist, sawed through the remaining strap.

Desiré floundered, got her right hand on the bar. She was hanging there.

“The trick was,” said the man, “to arrange the straps so that they wouldn’t shut off circulation, and to have a light enough anesthetic so the pain of hanging there would bring you immediately awake. It seems to have worked about right.”

“Please,” whispered Desiré through cracked lips. “Please.” She was looking down at the light and hard floor so far below. Her arms were aching and her fingers were growing numb.

“Did you see Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade or Batman?” asked the man. His head and shoulders seemed to be extended through some sort of access shaft.

“Please.” She was weeping.

“I’ll assume you did,” he continued in that insane, conversational tone. “Remember all the scenes where people grabbed other people’s hands on ledges and so forth? As soon as they had them, you knew the person was safe.” He shifted, pulled back a bit into the hatch.

“Please,” whimpered Desiré. She had already wet herself; now she was afraid she was going to soil herself.

“Well, the truth of it is,” said the man behind the mask, “that eighty-five percent of the American people can’t lift their own weight three feet. That’s an appalling figure, isn’t it, Desiré?”

The sound of her name made Desiré weep and blubber louder. “Please, please, please.” The fingers of her right hand had almost let go.

“What you do is,” said the man, “pull yourself up on that crossbar. You might try swinging over to this inspection shaft when I’m gone, but that’s a little risky if your arms are as tired as I expect they’ll be. Instead, why don’t you wedge yourself onto the top of the bar and just scream. This place is usually empty, the street’s too loud to hear shouts, but sometimes there are vagrants who get in. Someone will hear you sooner or later. Oops, no . . . hang on.”

Desiré’s right hand had slipped off. She screamed and found a handhold again.

“No,” she was crying loudly now. “I can’t . . . too heavy . . . please.”

“Sorry,” whispered the man. “I have an appointment.” The eyes behind the holes in the mask glanced down. “If you’re part of the eighty-five percent rather than the fifteen, I think the three-story fall won’t kill you. Probably break every bone in your body, but won’t kill. Best of luck.” He was gone.

Desiré screamed. Her fingers shifted on sharp metal. She tried to swing her legs up, remembering how she used to do it so easily on the schoolyard bars when she was a girl, but that had been twenty years and a hundred and twenty pounds ago. Her legs never got higher than her waist.

Finally, she hung there, fingers straining, body limp, the light swinging thirty-five feet below her sneakers.

Outside, if one had been listening, one would have heard a series of short screams lasting less than a minute, then one long final scream. Then there were only the street and city sounds again.

They were discussing movies in the teachers’ lounge. Mrs. Hopper and her friend Miss Milton said that movies were so foul-mouthed that they weren’t worth going to any longer. It had been years since either woman had seen anything other than a Disney film, and even those were getting terrible.

Ms. Bodan, who was much younger, thought that movies were better than ever. She had seen six over Christmas vacation. What did the Counselor think?

The Counselor looked up from his lunch. “Think about movies? I go to a lot of them.”

“Yes,” said Ms. Bodan, thinking that this was the first personal thing she’d learned about this man. “But what do you think about the trend in films over the past few years?”

The Counselor paused a moment from eating his salad. “Well, I think the trend is that they still show that we hate our children,” he said at last.

Ms. Bodan blinked. Mrs. Hopper and Miss Milton rolled their eyes. Here we go again, their glances said.

“How do they show that?” asked Ms. Bodan. She showed her class movies on the VCR every Friday afternoon. She was considered a “with-it” teacher.

The Counselor chewed slowly. He adjusted his glasses. “Well, if you don’t count The Bad Seed . . . the 1956 version with Patty McCormack, not the terrible made-for-TV thing in ’85 . . . if you don’t count it, then it probably started with Rosemary’s Baby in ’68. Even then, Mia Farrow was trying to save the baby. The real hatred started coming out in The Exorcist in ’73 and was completely obvious by the time of The Omen in ’76.”

Ms. Bodan stared at the man. “Hatred? You’re saying that movies show that we hate our kids?”

“Hate and fear them,” said the Counselor, spearing the last of his soggy green beans. “Not just the movies, of course. Think of all the ‘posessed children’ and ‘tormented children’ paperbacks by the likes of V.C. Andrews and John Saul . . .”

“My students like V.C. Andrews,” said Ms. Bodan, her voice thin. “They read his books all the time during Free Reading period.”

“Her books,” corrected the Counselor. “Have you ever read one?”

“Well, no, but the parents don’t seem to mind. The books come from home.”

The Counselor nodded, seemingly oblivious to the young teacher’s growing irritation. Mrs. Hopper and Miss Milton looked on approvingly; Ms. Bodan had been the last holdout on not chatting about the Counselor behind his back.

“Incest, torture, abuse, imprisonment,” said the Counselor between bites of the rubbery beans. “They’ve been bestsellers for years. But it’s the movies that have led the way in showing us how we feel about our kids. Satan-possessed infants . . . do you remember the audiences cheering when Gregory Peck raised the knife over the three-year-old in The Omen?” Ms. Bodan shook her head. Her lips were thin and white despite her lipstick.

“There have been a hundred since,” said the Counselor. “In recent years it’s been our teenagers we’ve killed. Think of the Jason movies, Freddy Kruger . . .”

Ms. Bodan set her coffee cup down with a slam. “Those are just . . . movies!”

“Yes,” agreed the Counselor. “And movies may be the surest way of testing an era’s collective subconscious. In the Depression we had a wealth of wish-fulfillment romances. Right before World War Two and during it, we had the Japanese and Nazis as the leering, subhuman villains. In recent years we’ve been sacrificing demon-possessed children and slaughtering teenagers. We may be the first generation that hates our offspring so much that we cheer those adults who attack children.”

Ms. Bodan stood suddenly, thrust her coffee cup on the mug shelf without rinsing it, and said, “I have to pick up my class.” She paused at the door. “You’re crazy, do you know that?” She flounced out, heels clicking on the tiled floor. The exit was ruined only slightly when she stopped and turned around to go back to the office to pick up the afternoon’s VHS tape.

Mrs. Hopper and Miss Milton stood with their trays poised, glanced at the Counselor, and gave each other a meaningful look. They smiled sweetly at him as they left.

The Counselor looked back at his tray. The piece of cake remained. He stayed to finish it.

“Myron? Goddamn you, Myron, where the fuck are you?”

Donnie “Pacino” Mantelli shouted into the dark first floor of the burned-out apartment building again before stepping in out of the gray light. He hated this rendezvous shit, but he couldn’t sell heroin on His Corner the way he did crack. And Myron had just stepped up to shit; he didn’t want to inconvenience one of his best customers this early in the game.

“Myron, you miserable little fuck. Where are you, babe?” Donnie went another few paces into the cold darkness. His new Brooks Elan MXT550 cross-trainers glowed white in the winter dimness. The shoes—always brand new—were like a trademark for Donnie and had been during his fifteen years in the business. He’d started late . . . almost nineteen when some of the street kids had been hustling dope when they were fourteen . . . but he’d made up for it by cornering the market in this part of town. He and his three franchised dealers were experts at getting entire generations hooked. It helped that—even at thirty-four—Donnie’s youthful looks and hip attire helped him blend in around the high school and middle school.

“Myron! I’m countin’ to three, babe, if you don’t show your sorry ass, I’m outta here.” If it had been Myron who’d suggested this place as a meeting place, Donnie wouldn’t have come. But Donnie had suggested it; he liked all the ways out. He was about ready to take one now. Normally one of his boys would’ve made the drop, but with shit the mark-up was too nice to let a middleman take his cut. “Myron?”

“Yo.” The voice in the darkness wasn’t Myron’s.

Donnie pulled out his Grendel P-10. The little semi-auto looked weird, more angles than a Star Trek phaser Cootie Mantizzo had once said, but it was small, double-action—which Cootie should’ve appreciated since he’d shot himself in the thigh once with his fucking Browning—and was pretty hard-hitting for such an easily concealed little thing. Donnie had loaded it with eleven .380 ACP cartridges and had already chambered the eleventh round.

“Myron isn’t coming,” said the voice. Some asshole, shorter than average height Donnie guessed from the sound of the voice, was moving around in the darkness by the far wall.

Donnie got out of the light and moved up against a wall himself. Two could play at this darkness game. He patted his pocket, feeling the parcel of horse there. Should I dump it? No, he realized, his sudden fright at the voice abating, if it’d been the cops or the DEA they wouldn’t be talking like this. They liked to leap out a few dozen strong, screaming Police, freeze! and all that shit. Besides, the cops had been taken care of in this neighborhood—Donnie had guarantees—and the DEA was too busy fucking around in the nigger neighborhoods.

“Myron OD’d last night,” said the voice from about thirty feet to Donnie’s right. “I came to pick up the shit instead. Come on back into the light and we’ll deal.”

You bet, fucker, thought Donnie. He crouched low and shifted left, his sneakers making only the softest noise. This wasn’t the cops, wasn’t one of Cootie’s boys . . . maybe old man Donatti was trying to make a comeback. Him or one of those greasers from the spick neighborhood.

Donnie shifted left, the Grendel cocked and extended. Say something else, asshole.

“I’ve brought the money,” said the man. He sounded wimpy. “Myron told me last week you were his dealer. He won’t mind now if you sell to me instead of him.”

Donnie had settled behind a stack of masonry blocks. There was no way anybody was going to sneak up on him here. He seriously doubted if this asshole had brought friends; they could’ve cut him off and jumped him when he came in if there’d been more than one. Now it was Donnie who had the free field of fire.

“I’m coming out,” said the voice. “Let’s meet in the middle.”

Yeah, you bet, thought Donnie. He steadied the Grendel on the top block and braced it in both hands the way his cop brother-in-law had taught him down at the police range. He’d bought the Grendel for close quarters work—and used it twice that way—but he knew that even with snap shots from waist level, he could put a pattern of eight or nine shots out of eleven into a body-sized mass at ten yards.

Ten yards was about where the circle of light from the doorway began.

“Yeah!” shouted Donnie. “Let’s meet in the middle.”

He aimed down the P-10’s fixed sights.

“Okay!” The voice was even more timid now. Maybe it was somebody wanting to do business. Only Donnie didn’t believe it.

A figure detached itself from the darkness. Little guy, maybe five-eight. He didn’t come all the way into the light, but paused at the edge of darkness there. Donnie’s eyes had adjusted to the darkness well enough to tell that the rest of the room seemed empty. The darkness wasn’t so dark that this guy could disappear again.

“I was lying, Donnie,” said the man, voice less timid now. “I came to bring you to justice.”

Bring me to justice? Fuck, what kind of old fart we got here?

“OK, let’s talk,” called Donnie, hoping the man would step forward just a bit more. He didn’t.

“OK,” Donnie said again, “let’s not talk.” He rapid-fired six times, ejected shells dropping around his crosstrainers.

He heard at least three of the slugs hit home. The man said “Oomph” and was knocked backward in a pratfall. He went down, arms flung wide, and stayed down.

Donnie waited a full minute and then came out in a crouch, circling the light, hammer back and watching the shadows. When no one moved or made a noise after another couple of minutes, Donnie moved quickly to the body.

The dude was white. Or rather, he was white under a bunch of green and yellow paint on his face. He had a bulky torso and was wearing some sort of soldier suit, camouflage crap, and Donnie could see three neat little holes—two in the chest and one lower on the belly—where the .380 slugs had gone in. His camouflage cap had come off when he’d gone down. So had a pair of glasses—round ones. They’d broken at the bridge. Donnie stayed a cool four feet away from the corpse but leaned over to pick up the cap.

Even as he was reaching, the bulkiness of the upper body registered. He remembered pictures his brother Anthony had sent home from Panama when he was in the service. Shit, flak jacket.

Donnie swiveled, swinging the Grendel, but the fucker rolled, moved faster than Donnie’d ever seen anyone move, grabbed his wrist, broke it, kicked away the gun, kicked Donnie’s legs out from under him.

Donnie actually heard the back of his own head hitting concrete.

Donnie came up out of it, feeling the headache before seeing the light or understanding that the noise that’d brought him around was a voice. Jesus Fuck, it hurt.

“I’ve got something for you,” said the same soft voice.

They were on a rooftop. Dim, winter sunlight. Other buildings around. Donnie started to scream. There was tape over his mouth.

The asshole in the tattered camouflage suit, flak jacket hanging free now and quite visible in the daylight, was filling a syringe from a small vial. Three other syringes were lying on a white cloth. Each had been painted red; Donnie couldn’t see the contents. He could see that the guy’s glasses had been mended with tape, which meant that Donnie’d been out for a few minutes.

Donnie closed his eyes again, willed unconsciousness to take him away from the pain.

“Uh-uh,” said the man and slapped him awake. He leaned closer as Donnie blinked up at camouflage paint. The cap was pulled low. Donnie could see his own reflection in the round glasses. His skin was as pale as the white tape across his mouth. He looked scared.

“I have to be going,” said the man, “so let’s get this over with.” Donnie squirmed, realizing through the pain that his hands and ankles were taped tightly behind him. His knees pointed at the sky. He wiggled and flopped, trying to turn over. The guy in the flak jacket set a heavy boot on his chest.

He had been moving the syringes around like shells in a shell game. Now he lifted all four of them in his left hand. Donnie saw that the protective plastic sleeve was still over the needle on each.

“Here’s the deal,” said the man. “I’ve filled all four of these. One has saline solution. No harm there. One has 200 cc of pure smack . . .”

Donnie’s eyes bulged and he began wiggling, thrashing, tugging at his taped wrists and making agonized sounds behind the tape. The man leaned on him with a heavy boot.

“One has saline solution, but with a nice, big air bubble . . .”

Donnie went wild again. The man moved his boot to Donnie’s throat. He had to lie still or have his larynx crushed.

“The final one has blood. O+, Donnie, just like yours. I checked. Of course, this came from an AIDS patient up at Mt. Carmel Hospital . . .” Donnie went wild despite the boot. The man set the heel over Donnie’s solar plexus and leaned a bit. Donnie exhaled through his nostrils and stared with eyes that were literally bulging out of their sockets.

The man removed the boot and leaned close, holding the four red syringes above Donnie’s face. “Your choice,” he said.

Donnie whimpered and thrashed. He couldn’t see the contents, couldn’t see which one held the clear saline solution. If any of them did. He tried to squirm away.

The man put a powerful hand on Donnie’s chest, squeezing him to the tar and gravel rooftop. “Come on, Donnie. You choose. Or I’ll choose for you. And you never know, I might cheat.”

Donnie tried to struggle upright, flopping with his hands and ankles behind him. His nose almost touched one of the syringes.

“OK,” said the man calmly. “I appreciate your cooperation.” He set the other three syringes aside and removed the cover on the needle. Donnie closed his eyes and felt himself being rolled over, his shirt being hiked up in the back.

“Look at it this way,” said the man. “You’ve got one chance in four. Which is a hell of a better deal than you gave Myron and a hundred other kids.”

There was a sudden prick at the base of his spine. Donnie tried to scream into the gag and then froze.

Nothing. Water. Fucking saline solu . . .

The massive overdose hit the base of his skull like a sledgehammer. For the briefest of instances, Donnie felt like his head was a baseball that had been knocked out of the park. He looked down expecting to see rooftops, parks, streets, the city flying beneath him.

At that second, the concentrated heroin reached his heart. Arteries exploded. Blood gushed up Donnie’s throat, out through the mucous linings, and erupted into his mouth. The tape held. Donnie’s eyes bled as he writhed one last time, blood geysering out of his nostrils in jets two yards long.

He slumped over, cheek against gravel. Blood pumped from his nose in smaller and smaller arcs for another several seconds.

The man had stepped back. Now he moved forward and rolled Donnie over with a boot. “Good choice.”

“Where’s Mr . . . whatshisname . . . the counselor?” asked Mrs. Hopper at lunch.

The secretary happened to be eating her lunch later than usual. “Oh, he called in sick today.” She leaned closer, her voice suddenly confidential. “I’ve seen this before with male teachers though.”

Mrs. Hopper and Miss Milton leaned their heads toward the secretary, trying to imagine what “male problem” they were about to learn of.

“It’s hunting season,” whispered Mrs. Perry, the secretary.

Mrs. Hopper and Miss Milton laughed. Ms. Bodan looked up rereading her novel.

“Imagine, our counselor going hunting,” said Miss Milton and giggled.

“Probably home watching TV,” said Mrs. Hopper.

“Old movies,” said Ms. Bodan with a flit of her head. She went back to her book.

Dr. Gerald Holse went hunting every year. The rest of the year he was the serious doctor, the earnest husband, the caring father . . . but for these three days he was just one of the boys. He and Ron and Art and Charlie would take their deer rifles and get away from it all for three days. They’d sit by the fire at night, drink Jack Daniels, tell a few stones, and generally let the tension of the professional world drain away. If they could kill a few deer, so much the better.

This morning, the sky gray in its slow pre-dawn paling and the air cold as a proverbial witch’s tit, Dr. Holse was sitting in his position—behind some shrubs looking down an east slope at a clearing—and wishing he hadn’t stayed up so late bullshitting and passing the bottle last night. His head hurt. His eyes hurt. His hair hurt.

Dr. Holse pulled off his gloves, breathed on his hands, set them briefly on the stock of his .30-.06, touched the telescopic sight almost reverently, and then pulled his orange gloves back on. Goddamn it was cold.

He’d been there about half an hour and was considering walking back over the hill to check on Art or one of the other guys when he thought he heard a noise. He froze, then lifted the rifle ever so slightly. Had something rustled on the other side of the clearing? Charlie had seen a big three-point buck down this way yesterday, and since two of the guys had already bagged a deer, they’d given him this spot.

Nothing moved. After several minutes, Dr. Holse relaxed.

Sitting there as the morning light began to touch the hillside, the doctor found himself thinking of his home—his beautiful home—and his wife, a woman any doctor would be proud to have, his practice—pulled in almost $600,000 before taxes last year, his stocks, real estate investments, and his daughter.

Dr. Holse shifted slightly, feeling the excitement building in his groin. At first he tried not to think about her, tried to remember what patients he’d be seeing on Wednesday, but then he relaxed and let the memories and fantasies work.

Little Jennifer. She’d always been the most beautiful of daughters. Doris, his wife, had even entered Jennifer in the civic Beautiful Baby contest when the child was three, and she had come in second, right behind a girl who’d gone on to a modeling career.

Dr. Holse was glad that Jennifer hadn’t received all that attention. It was as if her beauty was his and his alone. It wasn’t until three years ago when she was eleven, just starting puberty, that month when Doris was away visiting her sister in Toronto, that the doctor had first gone into his only child’s bedroom with that on his mind.

God, she was beautiful. He’d caught her getting ready for bed, her nightgown lifted over her head. Her breasts were little more than soft mounds, the nipples not yet raised from the tender pink areolae. Her pubic hair was not even V-shaped yet, merely a small line of fuzz rising above the tenderest vulva Holse had seen in all of his years of examining women and girls.

She had peeked out of the neck of the nightgown with wide, startled eyes. Dr. Holse had lifted it back over her head, touched her lips with a single finger, hushing her. Then he had touched her elsewhere. Later, he had guided her hand where he wanted it.

It had been like a game to the doctor: even the terrible guilt that had sent him to the prescription cabinet those first weeks had seemed like part of the game. So was hiding everything from Doris when she returned. But mostly it was waiting, postponing the ultimate, putting it off for weeks past the point when he thought he could wait no longer.

It was as if Jennifer was part of the game. At first she had wept, threatened to tell her mother or teachers. Dr. Holse had explained to her what happened to girls who did that: the foster homes, the public humiliation, and the simple fact that no husband or family would ever want her after such a thing was revealed. Now, three years later, more than two years after that first time he had penetrated her on a “camping trip” they had spent at the Holiday Inn on the outskirts of town, Holse knew that Jennifer didn’t believe in those dire warnings any longer. She didn’t believe the foster home was waiting for her.

But Dr. Holse had bet on the fact that shame and the habit of lying would become a habit for both of them. And it had.

He had an erection now, just thinking about it. Jennifer had been locking her door in recent weeks, but the doctor had quietly had the lock removed. Doris must have noticed something. Many was the time that Holse believed that she knew; but Doris had her own tastes, many of them were expensive, and he knew she put the appearance of family happiness far above the reality. She’d been talking a lot recently about Jennifer choosing a college, living away from home. Dr. Holse only smiled indulgently. That was at least two and a half years away.

The doctor pulled out the silver flask the nurses at the clinic had given him on his fortieth birthday. It had been an expensive gag, but Dr. Holse had made a tradition of bringing it on his deer-hunting outings. He took a drink now. Hair of the dog.

Something crackled and moved in the brush below.

Dr. Holse rose to one knee, rifle coming across his chest. He was careful hunting, never firing before complete identification of the target the way Art or Charlie sometimes did.

A beautiful six-point buck strolled into the clearing, head up, black eyes catching the light.

Dr. Holse held his breath, bringing the rifle to his shoulder in a single movement. The creature was upwind of him. He was sure the buck couldn’t see him through the shrubs. It was a beautiful shot of about twenty yards.

Dr. Holse slipped off the safety and set the creature’s heart in the crosshairs. Charlie would shit bricks that he’d given up this site.

Just as the doctor’s finger was beginning to apply pressure to the trigger, there was a sudden wasp sting on his neck. He blinked, realized the insect was still there, still stinging, and—taking care to keep the rifle in place with his left hand and shoulder—raised his right hand to brush the damn bug away.

He felt feathers under his fingertips. He had time to tug the dart out, stare at it a second, and think This is the stupidest damn joke Ron’s ever pulled when the buck, alarmed by something, bolted away through the underbrush.

Dr. Holse started to lift the rifle to get off a snap shot. The rifle had grown too heavy. Cursing, he started to turn to tell Ron what a stupid fucking non-gag he thought this was.

Turning, the world and sky lost their balance and Dr. Holse went face first into the frost-rimmed grass. His rifle fell from suddenly nerveless hands. From where he lay, one cheek against the dirt, he could see uphill out of his left eye. Even blinking seemed impossible. There was no pain other than a vague pins and needles twitching, but he could still feel things. He just couldn’t move for Chrissakes.

Curare, thought some calm, medical part of his brain. Or maybe some commercial animal tranquilizer. Probably the latter since his brain was alert and he still had sensation in most parts of his body. It wouldn’t last long then: a few minutes, half hour at most. Then Ron or Art or whoever pulled this prank was going to get the thrashing of his life.

A stranger in camouflage garb came out of the trees three meters uphill from Dr. Holse and crouched next to him. The doctor could clearly see the combat boots, the black-banded Timex on the thick wrist, the camouflage blouse. The quick glimpse of the man’s face had left only a memory of the rising sun glinting on a pair of round-lensed glasses.

“This won’t take long,” whispered the man. “Your friends moved down into the valley on the far side of the hill. We’ll call them when I’m done.”

Dr. Holse felt his mind veer like a car on black ice. This was insane, something out of a bad movie on cable. He had no enemies, professional or personal. Dr. Gerald Holse was one of the best-liked and most respected men in his community. He wanted to shout this at the stranger, to offer money, to bargain, to use his rhetorical skills on this asshole.

He couldn’t move. His cheek twitched from random nerve-firings.

The man in combat camouflage removed a curved knife from his web belt. Dr. Holse recognized the sort of blade. It was a skinning knife. He had watched Art dress out the deer each year with just such a knife, watching with professional interest as the blade easily separated hide and membrane from striated muscle tissue.

Dr. Holse would have screamed then, tried to scream, but he only succeeded in letting his bladder release.

As if sensing the doctor’s humiliation, the man in camouflage rolled him over, unzipped his wet trousers, and tugged them down.

The doctor could see only sky and a bit of the man’s left shoulder. His mind was flitting to and fro like a dog in a field full of rabbits. He did not believe this.

“Believe it,” whispered the man. “Believe it and remember all those times with your daughter. Your child. Your child who tried to kill herself last night with sleeping pills while you were gone.” The paint-streaked face leaned closer, the lenses showing the sun rising through bare branches. “Believe it,” whispered the man. “And if you don’t believe, I’ll leave a couple of things in your shirt pocket to convince you later.”

The man bent out of Dr. Holse’s line of sight.

He’s leaving, thought the doctor. He came to scare me, and he did, and he’s left. He listened for the sound of boots on frozen grass.

The first incision was on the upper perineum, just below the scrotum. Dr. Holse could follow the progress of the blade quite easily as it dug deep, cut, severed, sliced upward. Whatever the tranquilizer had been, it had little or no anaesthetic qualities whatsoever.

Bill Mastyk, the principal of Myer Middle School, was in his office when the police arrived. There were four of them, two plainclothes detectives who did the talking and two other giants who simply filled the open doorway and sent out rays of physical menace which made Mastyk damned glad that he wasn’t their prey.

They showed Mastyk the warrant, the police profile, the excerpts from the Counselor’s military records—the principal was amazed to learn that the little man had served in Tehran itself, preparing the way for the aborted hostage rescue mission, killing three double agents before escaping himself—and then they showed him the positive identification by witnesses, including a Mrs. Desiré Reynolds who, they told him, was still in the hospital recovering from an assault months earlier.

“The Counselor,” said Mastyk. He realized how hoarse he’d sounded. “Our Counselor?”

The closer of the two detectives nodded. “Eleven murders, over three dozen serious assaults. To be honest, it was the computer that finally made the connection with the school districts. His residence in each district correlates perfectly with the chain of attacks.”

The principal nodded, although he understood nothing. “What motive . . .”

The other detective slid a folder across Mastyk’s desk. “That’s his real name. He was an abused child . . . finally sent to a series of foster homes when he was nine. That was after he’d watched his parents beat his younger sister to death. Then the Marines and detached service. Then . . . this.”

Mastyk nodded again, licked his lips. “OK. What now?”

“Now we go pick him up,” said the first detective. “We know he’s in the building. Black and whites have the grounds surrounded.”

Mastyk felt panic rise. What would the papers say? He’d be on the news . . . the principal with a murderer on his staff! MASTYK HIRES SERIAL KILLER TO COUNSEL CHILDREN. Jesus, what would the superintendent say. What would his own wife say?

“Ready?” said the second detective.

Mastyk looked at the two giants in the doorway. He’d bring giants, too, if he was trying to apprehend a murderer. The Counselor? Mastyk shook his head. “Why here, for God’s sake? Why at school? Why not take him at home or somewhere? The children . . .”

The first detective twitched a smile. “In England, the cops try to take their suspects at home. Away from everyone. Surrounded. In this country, Mr. Mastyk, that’s usually allowing the suspect to get into his arsenal. And we’re fairly certain that he’s not armed here.”

“Fairly certain . . .” was all that Mastyk could squeak.

“Besides,” said the second detective, “the one thing we know about this guy is that he’s got a hang-up about kids getting hurt. Our resident psychiatrist says that it’s almost certain that he wouldn’t put up a fight when there was any chance of a kid getting caught in the middle.”

“Almost certain . . .” managed Mastyk.

“Let’s go,” said the first detective, all but lifting the principal out of his chair. He nodded toward the giants and the five men moved in a wedge down the empty hallways. “Show us the room, we’ll make sure he’s there, then stand back.”

Mastyk nodded and showed the way.

The Counselor did not put up a fight.

He rose when the four detectives entered and seemed about to offer his hand. The two big men seized him, twisted his arm behind his back, kicked his legs apart, propped him against the wall, cuffed him with his hands behind his back, and frisked him.

“He’s clean,” said Sergeant Dunning. He pulled the Counselor around and slammed him into a chair while Lieutenant Baker Mirandized him and Captain Detweiler went through the desk quickly. No weapons. No alcohol or drugs. Nothing out of place except for some plastic vampire teeth that looked as if they’d been taken from a student, dropped in a drawer, and forgotten.

“Anything to say before we go?” said Detweiler.

The Counselor shook his head. His glasses had slid down on his nose. Sergeant Dunning shoved them back up.

“Let’s go,” said Detweiler.

Mr. Mastyk was in the hall, hands flexing, his face pale beneath his ginger mustache. “Have you . . . did you . . . will you be . . .”

“Clear these kids out of here,” said the Captain, nodding toward the students who had emerged from doorways.

Mastyk made shooing motions, then shouted for children to return to their rooms.

“What the fuck is this, between periods or something?” asked the other sergeant, Luknow, as the hall filled with kids.

“This is last period. Everyone’s in homeroom,” said Mastyk, still making shooing motions with his arms. Fifth, sixth, and seventh graders flowed around him and stared at the flying wedge of police bodies with the Counselor in the middle.

“Get them out of the way. Now,” snapped Lieutenant Baker. More kids were flowing into the narrow hall every second. Little kids, gawky kids, kids underfoot and pressing closer. The flying wedge tried to back into the storage room that was the Counselor’s office, but there was a solid mass of kids behind them. The noise in the hallway was loud, not random.

Mr. Mastyk fell back against the police detectives.

“Fuck this,” said Sergeant Dunning and released one hand from the prisoner to reach for his .38.

“Stop!” screamed the Captain, slapping at the sergeant’s arm. “Are you out of your fucking mind?”

The kids were swarming now. Some of them were big, beefy kids, little linebackers, others were agile little tight ends that got under the linked arms the three lead detectives and Mastyk had raised as a barrier.

There were no barriers for this undersized mob. The hallway was filled with kids, hundreds of kids. They let out a noise and rushed, jumping, passing smaller bodies above them. Even the Counselor seemed to be shouting NO! along with the terrified principal and detectives.

Lieutenant Baker managed to get his radio out of his coat pocket. He broke squelch, thumbed the preset frequency. A little hand twisted the radio out of his grasp. Someone not so little jumped on his back.

Sergeant Dunning was the last to go down. Detweiler had a last glimpse of him, a hulking, man-shaped mass of kids, fucking kids, girls as well as boys, leaping, jumping, mobbing, clinging.

Then they were all down, Mastyk covering his face as principals are wont to do; the rest of the men covering their kidneys and genitals, as cops are wont to do.

Baker and Detweiler fully expected to die then, trompled by the sheer weight of numbers and tiny little Keds-covered feet, but after a moment of total confusion and terror, the mob abated, the tidal wave receded, the kids were gone.

“What the fuck,” said Dunning, the biggest man on the Metropolitan force. He was spitting blood from a split lip.

Captain Detweiler got to his knees, found a wall to pull himself up.

The Counselor was gone, of course. Washed away with the tsunami of kids. It took a minute for Detweiler to find his radio; it was in a drinking fountain.

He called the lieutenant outside in charge of the black and whites.

“Nossir,” came the lieutenant’s voice. “Nothing but that mob of kids when school let out.”

Mr. Mastyk tried to get to his feet but gave it up and sat on the tile. He had heard the radio squawk its message. He glanced at his watch, blinking stupidly. “But school isn’t out for another twenty minutes . . .”

Detweiler, Baker, and the others went to the front door. The hallways were empty with that aloneness unique to an empty school. “We’ll search the school,” Dunning was saying. He was on the radio now, alerting the black and whites, calling in reinforcements.

Captain Detweiler nodded, standing a minute at the open door. It was getting dark already in the early December rush of twilight. The outside air smelled fresh with that just-released-from-school smell Detweiler remembered from his childhood. Suddenly his childhood seemed not so long ago or far away, although God knows there were enough things he wanted to forget about it.

Detweiler looked at Baker, who’d just gotten off his own tactical radio. “What day is it today, Bill?”

Baker frowned at him. “Wednesday.”

“Yeah, but what’s the date?” Detweiler made a gesture. “I’ll need it for the report.”

“December seven,” said the lieutenant. Uniformed policeman were rushing toward the building, searching the shrubs and bushes, moving into the city park across the street. Detweiler could see flashing lights as more units arrived. Somewhere a siren growled.

Mr. Mastyk was standing in the doorway, looking out into the darkness. Now he turned with a strange expression on his face.

“The first day of the war.”

Three of the detectives stared at the principal as if he were crazy. Darkness continued to fall. From somewhere in the park, a sound came through the cold evening air. Clear, sharp, too suddenly silenced, it was the unmistakable sound of a child laughing.